Dan A. Ballard Collection of Railroad Memorabilia & Wage Information 5943
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
Dan A. Ballard Collection of Railroad Memorabilia & Wage Information
1933-1987
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
Ballard, Dan A.
5943
0.5 cubic feet
0.3 linear ft.
Memorabilia, records (documents).
Collection of railroad memorabilia collected by Dan Ballard and Dan Alber Ballard, Jr. from their time working on the Illinois Central Railroad, Louisiana Division
5736596
General
Contact Information:
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation and Archives Martin P. Catherwood Library 227 Ives Hall Cornell University Ithaca, NY 14853 (607) 255-3183 kheel_center@cornell.edu http://www.ilr.cornell.edu/library/kheel-center
Compiled by:
E. Parker, June 06, 2017
EAD encoding:
Kheel Staff, June 06, 2017
Biographical / Historical
Dan Ballard, Sr. and his son, Dan Allbert Ballard, Jr., were both employees on the Illinois Central Railroad. Dan Ballard, Sr. was born on September 11, 1899 in Louisiana. He married Lillie Minor in 1923 and had four children. Their oldest, Dan Albert ballard, Jr., was born on June 7, 1924 in New Orleans, Louisiana. Dan Ballard, Sr. was employed as a cinder pit man, helper, and staionary engineer in the New Orleans Passenger Terminal. Dan Albert Ballard, Jr. was employed as a coach cleaner at the New Orleans Passenger Terminal. Both were active union members in their respective crafts: Ballard, Sr. in the International Brotherhood of Firemen and Oilers; Ballard, Jr. in the Brotherhood Railway Carmen of America. Dan Albert Ballard, Jr.'s grandon, Edward Kennedy, donated these materials to the Kheel Center. Mr. Kennedy is an alumnus of Cornell's ILR School.
Scope and Contents
Inclusive date range: 1933-1987
Bulk dates: 1942-1955
This collection consists of the memoribilia collected by Dan Ballard, Sr. and his son, Dan Albert Ballard, Jr. over the course of their careers as employees of the Illinois Central Railroad, Louisiana Division and as union members. Dan Ballard, Sr. belonged to the International Brotherhood of Firemen and Oilers, and was one of the members who was named of their certificate of affiliation with the AFL-CIO, which is found in this collection. Dan Albert Ballard, Jr. was a member of the Brotherhood Railway Carmen of America, and his union dues reciepts are found in this collection. Also found in this collection are pay stubs, certificate of service months and wages from the U.S. Railroad Retirement Board, and Dan Ballard Sr.'s Designation or Change of Beneficiary form for the U.S. Railroad Retirement Board. In addition to these personal records, this collection also contains membership and union dues cards from the International Brotherhood of Firemen and Oilers from other union members, a collection of seniority lists from the New Orleans Passenger Terminal from 1970, and time tables for other railroads. Of particular note is the employee's train pass issued to Dan Albert Ballard, Jr, identifying him as an African-American employee and limiting the train cars in which he was permitted to travel.
Conditions Governing Access
Access to the collections in the Kheel Center is restricted. Please contact a reference archivist for access to these materials.
Related Materials
Related Collections: 6046: Archives Union File (AUF) 5197: Illinois Central Gulf Railroad Miscellany 5295: Illinois Central Gulf Railroad Company Selected Personnel Files
Railroads; African Americans -- Employment; Railroads -- United States -- Employees; Ballard, Dan Albert, 1924-; Ballard, Dan, 1899-1990; United States. Railroad Retirement Board; AFL-CIO; Illinois Central Railroad Company; Louisville and Nashville Railroad Company; Baltimore and Ohio Railroad Company; Brotherhood Railway Carmen of the United States and Canada; International Brotherhood of Firemen and Oilers
5736596
- Louisville and Nashville Railroad, The Dixie Line, Passenger Train Time Tables, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Baltimore and Ohio Railroad, Train Schedules, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  Scope and Contents
  Between Detroit, Toledo, Dayton, Cincinnati. Connections via L&N RR between Cincinnati and New Orleans
- Illinois Central Railroad, Service Annual Pass, 1950-1951 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  "For Dan Ballard, Jr. (Col.), good only in coaches, between stations on Louisiana Division"
- U.S. Railroad Retirement Board, Certificate of Service Months and Wages, 1942-1954 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Illinois Central, Withholding Statement, 1946-1954 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Illinois Central, Statement of Earnings and Deductions, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- International Brotherhood of Firemen and Oilers, Union Membership and Dues Cards, 1942-1955 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Brotherhood Railway Carmen of America, Coach Cleaners' Due Receipts, 1951-1954 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Constitution of the Brotherhood Railway carmen of the United States and Canada, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- U.S. Railroad Retirement Board, Designation or Change of Beneficiary, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Tax receipt and earnings statement, 1955-1978 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- International Brotherhood of Firemen, Oilers, Helpers, Round House, and Railroad Shop Laborers Certificate of Affiliation with the AFL-CIO, 1933 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  Local Union No. 942, New Orleans, Louisiana
- New Orleans Union Passenger Terminal, Bulletins and Seniority Rosters, 1954-1970 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- "Teller" Cloth Armband (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Union Memorabilia, 1983-1987 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  Brotherhood Railway Carmen of the United States and Canada, Twenty-Seventh Convention, Kansas City, MO, August 1983 - Ashtray; BRAC 28th Regular Convention, Hollywood, FL, July 27-31, 1987 - Money Clip.